Okay, so in the last one we talked about
how an if statement can control the flow
of your code. I'm going to delete this
and we're going to do a different um
example here. Um so we're going to
gather a student's GPA.
GPA. So let's store that in a variable.
So we'll say let GPA equal um and the
GPA is going to be a float. So, I'm
going to parse float and then I'm going
to prompt
what is your GPA.
Now, if they have a high enough GPA,
let's say like a 3.5, uh we'll give them
a scholarship. So, we'll say if GPA is
greater than 3.5,
and then we'll put our curly braces. So,
now whatever happens in between these
curly braces will only happen if they
have a GPA of above 3.5. So, we're going
to alert um congrats.
Here is a scholarship.
We'll save that and
we'll visit our website and it says,
"What is your GPA?" We'll enter 3.8.
Congrats. Here's your scholarship. Okay,
great. So, we know that that portion
works.
But what if we want to do something if
they don't have a high enough GPA? What
if we want to tell them keep working on
your grades, maybe next year? Um,
well, there's a way that you can do
that. So, after this if, we put curly
braces. At the end of those curly
braces, we can type something to do if
all else fails. And we call this else.
So, we'll say if their GPA is higher
than 3.5, tell them congratulations,
here's a scholarship. If it's not higher
than 3.5, then we want to say, "Sorry,
maybe next year."
So, we'll save that. We'll come over
here. What is our GPA? 3.5.
Nope. Sorry, maybe next year. So, the
reason that happened is because I said
it has to be greater than 3.5. So, if
it's exactly 3.5, then this is not true,
which means it's going to come here and
say, "Sorry, maybe next year." So,
unfortunately, it looks like we don't
have a scholarship this time. Let's
reload our page. What is your GPA? 3.51.
Congratulations. Here's your
scholarship. Um, and that is how if and
else statements work. So, if statements
are used for making a decision.
Elsements are attached to an if
statement and they run when no other
condition is met. Sometimes there are
times where you will want to check more
than one condition. And in the next
video we'll talk about that.